so let's look at a real example of a
hierarchical predictor we will look at
intel's pentium m processor that has
these predictors first it has
a cheap predictor that contains just two
bit counters then it has a local history
predictor and a global history predictor
so what the processor is doing is it has
a large array of two bit counters
a local history predictor that stores
the local history for each branch and an
array of two-bit counters for different
histories and the global history
predictor with a global history that is
longer than the local histories here and
also an array of counters for that
predictor
so if we try to predict a single branch
what we would do is we would look up
the pc for that branch in the two bit
counter array we will also try to look
up the local predictor and the global
predictor prediction
and then we form the actual prediction
for the processor by using the result of
the global predictor if the global
predictor says that the branch is
predicted here and for that what we do
is we keep another array here that is
just saying whether this branch so this
is kind of like a tag array that says
whether this branch is going to be
predicted by the global predictor
if the global predictor does not have a
matching tag that means that this branch
was not inserted in the global predictor
in which case we shouldn't use it
if that happens we will use the
prediction from the local predictor
which will also have a tag array that
says whether this predictor should be
predicted by the local predictor and if
so
then we use that otherwise if the branch
is not in the local predictor we just
use the result of the two-bit counter
when we update the predictor however
what we do is we update the two-bit
counter if we
have the branch in the local predictor
we update the local predictor if we have
the branch in the global predictor we
update the global predictor but then
what happens is if we are using the
two-bit counter and the branch is not in
the local predictor then what we do is
if the two-bit counter is mispredicting
the branch we insert it into the local
predictor so now the branch will be
present here next time
if the local predictor is not giving us
good prediction for this branch then we
insert the branch into the global
predictor so what's going to happen is
pretty much branches that are almost
perfectly predictable by two-bit
counters and that's a lot of branches
for example
every
always taken branch or branch that is
dominantly taken is going to be mostly
predicted by the 2-bit predictor so we
never really need to consult the local
and global predictors and that saves
space in these predictors
for other branches that need them
saving space means that we can have a
lot fewer of the two bit entries than
the history entries than we would
otherwise need if we were trying to
predict all the branches with the local
or even the global predictor so how do
we say whether the branch is present or
not well what we really do is we insert
some bits of the branch's address
into the
corresponding line of the predictor so
the history entry here we will index
with some bits of the pc to find the
history and in that same entry we will
also insert some of the upper bits of
the pc so that different branches that
map to this entry only one of them gets
to be predicted by this entry the rest
of them say that they are not found here
so the idea is that if most of the
branches that end up mapping to this
entry are really predictable by the two
bit predictor then we don't really need
to use this entry for those branches